<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="https://alix-tz.github.io/phd/assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>A research (b)log (Posts about milestone)</title><link>https://alix-tz.github.io/phd/</link><description></description><atom:link href="https://alix-tz.github.io/phd/categories/cat_milestone.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><copyright>Contents © 2025 &lt;a href="https://alix-tz.github.io/phd/"&gt;Alix Chagué&lt;/a&gt; CC-BY</copyright><lastBuildDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 18:20:21 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>015 - Block post and comprehensive Exam</title><link>https://alix-tz.github.io/phd/posts/015/</link><dc:creator>Alix Chagué</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;When I created this blog last year, I wanted to post regularly on it. Something like once a month or once every other month. I didn't want to put pressure on myself for writing, but I also wanted to make sure that this blog would be alive. I often have ideas for topics for a post. But then, when comes the time to write, I blank out. It's not exactly that I don't know where to start, it's just that I sometimes can't figure out what is the message I want to convey. Like, if I have to summarize my blog post in 2 lines, what's the take-away? I get stuck when I cannot find an answer,but maybe I shouldn't worry that much about it. It's my blog after all, and maybe the message will come by the time I'm done writing. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, without further ado, let's dive in: I was &lt;em&gt;super&lt;/em&gt; excited this Summer after passing my comprehensive exam. I really wanted to write a post about it. I had a really packed Spring and beginning of Summer between going back to Montreal, teaching a class there, attending a Summer school, going to the DH2023 conference in Austria where I presented a short paper, a long paper and organized a workshop (big up to Thibault who was by my sides through all these Austrian adventures). And all of it culminated with that comprehensive exam in the middle of August. I really wanted to share how that went.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But then, vacations, working on new deadlines, more vacations, more deadlines... And now it's already November and I don't know anymore what it was that I wanted to share about that exam. Aside from the fact that I passed it and that it's a pretty big milestone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The comprehensive examination, which is called "Examen de synthèse" in French, is not something common in France. In France, we now have a sort of yearly evaluation called the "Comité de Suivi Individuel" (or CSI), which is not a scholar evaluation but more of a check-up with your supervisors and a committee&lt;sup id="fnref:CSI"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="https://alix-tz.github.io/phd/posts/015/#fn:CSI"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; in charge of making sure that everything is alright. The reason I bring it alongside the Examen de Synthèse is because I also had my first CSI this Summer (at the very end of June). In France, you have to have a positive evaluation from the CSI in order to enroll in a new year of doctoral studies. Each year. But, actually the CSI and the Examen de Synthèse are not really that comparable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Examen de Synthèse is a "real" examination and it happens only once during your doctoral curriculum. In my program at the University of Montréal, in 2023, it consisted in several phases.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First of all, there is a phase dedicated to the composition of the jury. I had the pleasure to be examined not only by my three supervisors (Laurent Romary, Emmanuel Chateau-Dutier and Michael Sinatra), but also by &lt;a href="https://vitalirosati.com/"&gt;Marcello Vitali Rosati&lt;/a&gt;, from the University of Montréal, who acted as president, and &lt;a href="https://www.uqar.ca/universite/a-propos-de-l-uqar/departements/departement-des-lettres-et-humanites/gohier-maxime"&gt;Maxime Gohier&lt;/a&gt; from the University of Quebec in Rimouski. I must signal that my only regret is not to have been able to have a better gender parity in my jury. This is something I really hope to fix for my defense, but I will probably have other occasions to discuss this topic in the future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, once the jury is composed, and once a calendar has been agreed on (I think &lt;em&gt;that&lt;/em&gt; was actually the most stressful part for me because of all the other things I had this Summer), a count down begins. First, I had to turn in three documents:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a 12-15 page-long essay on my research project;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a 30-reference long bibliography on the field of the Digital Humanities; and&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a short presentation of a proposed "practical" analysis.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then a week later, the jury sent a question.&lt;sup id="fnref:question"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="https://alix-tz.github.io/phd/posts/015/#fn:question"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; I was given 1 week (168h exactly) to think about this question and write a response in the form of a 10-15 page-long essay. The jury had between a week and two weeks to read the response before an oral examination took place (on Zoom).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The oral examination has some similarities with a PhD defense. It started with a 20 minute long presentation that I gave where I summarized my research project (10 minutes) and presented a technical analysis (10 minutes). I chose to focus my technical presentation on an experiment I have been conducting and on which I hope to communicate more in the near future. Then, after my presentation, there were two rounds of questions about my research project, my experiment or about the answer I formulated in my essay.&lt;sup id="fnref:more"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="https://alix-tz.github.io/phd/posts/015/#fn:more"&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am very happy that such an examination exists in the North American program. It may seem like a lot of stress (and it is), but I found that it is also a very good milestone to progress a lot towards the formalization of a research project. The oral examination is a great opportunity to present a project to people who don't necessarily know what you have been up to before, and it's a really really great occasion to get feedback.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, the question that is sent by the jury, in the case of my program, is thought as a way to get you to think about a topic or a question that is either not tackled enough by your research proposal, or it's an invitation to consider new angles. You're not expected to turn in the perfect answer, of course, with barely a week to write it. But it forces you to form an opinion, explore possible hypotheses and may turn later into a whole chapter for your thesis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The comprehensive exam is a pass/no pass type of examination. There is no grade and if you fail, you can take it a second time. Like I said before at the beginning of this post, I passed. Therefore, starting from Fall 2023, I am now able to enroll as a "en rédaction" student (writing status) which has several consequences. Some seem very symbolic: for example, in English, I can now call myself a PhD candidate instead of a PhD student. But others not so much: tuitions for this new status are &lt;a href="https://registraire.umontreal.ca/droits-de-scolarite/couts-des-etudes/#c14807"&gt;much lower&lt;/a&gt; than when enrolling as a full-time student, dropping from 1,440$CA/trimester to 512$CA/trimester, and I believe this officially gives me the right to teach at graduate level.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The comprehensive exam also marks the end of the phase during which I had to take courses. Now, with this new status, I am invited to focus solely on the redaction of my thesis, which opens up a whole new chapter for my PhD curriculum.&lt;sup id="fnref:pun"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="https://alix-tz.github.io/phd/posts/015/#fn:pun"&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:CSI"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I want to take this occasion to also thank &lt;a href="https://ciham.cnrs.fr/annuaire/membres_statutaires/ariane-pinche/"&gt;Ariane Pinche&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://pro.univ-lille.fr/joana-casenave"&gt;Joana Casenave&lt;/a&gt;, who were willing to be the members of my committee for the CSI, for their precious feedback! :) &lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="https://alix-tz.github.io/phd/posts/015/#fnref:CSI" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:question"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The question was the following: "&lt;em&gt;Dans votre projet de recherche apparaît une tension importante: celle entre la spécificité des besoins particuliers de chaque projet et la volonté -- et la nécessité -- de produire des approches généralisables, qui puissent être employées dans le cadre de plusieurs projets. En vous appuyant sur votre bibliographie, et en vous concentrant notamment sur le cas du HTR, pourriez-vous analyser cette tension en soulevant en particulier la question de la littératie demandée (notamment dans la gestion des données) pour pouvoir personnaliser des approches computationnelles aussi complexes que les technologies HTR?&lt;/em&gt;" &lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="https://alix-tz.github.io/phd/posts/015/#fnref:question" title="Jump back to footnote 2 in the text"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:more"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I want publish on my blog the documents I created for the comprehensive exam, but I need to find the best way to do it. I'll post an announcement when it will be available. &lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="https://alix-tz.github.io/phd/posts/015/#fnref:more" title="Jump back to footnote 3 in the text"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:pun"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thank you Jennifer for this wonderful pun! ;) &lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="https://alix-tz.github.io/phd/posts/015/#fnref:pun" title="Jump back to footnote 4 in the text"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>cotutelle</category><category>courses</category><guid>https://alix-tz.github.io/phd/posts/015/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 07 Nov 2023 13:15:06 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>009 - Looking back to 2022</title><link>https://alix-tz.github.io/phd/posts/009/</link><dc:creator>Alix Chagué</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;Over the past decade, I've started a tradition of taking a sort-of-day-long hike on the 1st of January. There is always a chance that the weather won't be on my side, but I like the idea of starting the year peacefully and embracing nature.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before starting 2023 though, and without much originality, I wanted to dedicate a last post for 2022 to looking back to my first full year of phD and focus on its biggest highlights as far as my phD project is concerned.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, the year sure didn't look like anything I had expected! I don't think I had envisioned any of what my trips to Montréal have brought me... but also how much they consume of the time available to actually work on my research project. As you will see, it is not necessarily a bad thing - I actually want to focus on the good parts - but it doesn't mean that it was easy to wrap my head around it.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I spent two thirds of the 2022 in Montréal: 8 months out of 12, with what looks right now like a super short 4 months of Summer in France in the middle. I specify that it was Summer because, you know, ... July and August, they're not usual months.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Overall, 2022 passed in the blink of an eye.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I spent a lot of time in class or preparing for class or working on final projects. Indeed, I took 4 classes out of the 5 required by the Université de Montréal, and attended 1 as an auditor.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;SCI6304 was a bibliometry class taught by Vincent Larivière;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;MSL6523 was a Digital Museology class conducted by Emmanuel Chateau-Dutier;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;LCO6525 was a Compared Chinese Literature class given by Victoria-Oana Lupascu;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;HNU7000 was a class focused on the Epistemology of the Digital Humanities lead by Michael E. Sinatra;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;and SCI6203, the extra class, was about AI and textual data, it was given by Dominic Forest.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As you can see, they were very diverse but I think I learned quite a few things from them that I will be able to use more or less directly for my research.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In HNU7000, we often had to write or present critical summaries of articles or conferences and in LCO6525, we were asked to turn in a "annotated bibliography" (at least 400 words for 6 references related to the topic of our final paper) halfway through the semester. With these exercises, I think I found a better way to summarize articles or books I read. I can still improve the "critical" aspect of the exercise, but I think I got better at summarizing what was actually relevant to me when I read. Now, I hope to publish some of these future summaries here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In SCI6304, my final project consisted in a bibliometric investigation on the publications on HTR over the past 40 years. I would like to publish the result as an article, which is a project for 2023. But I can already see that doing so, I gained a much better understanding of the field(s) related to my research project, I found some keywords that I need to investigate and I added a bunch of references to my potentially-to-read list.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In MSL6523, the final poject consisted in a blog post for &lt;a href="https://medium.com/museonum"&gt;Museonum&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a href="https://medium.com/museonum/intelligence-artificielle-et-intelligence-collective-des-nouveaux-eldorados-pour-rendre-les-c8c4e214d4e6"&gt;Mine&lt;/a&gt; was focused on the current use of automatic transcription and crowdsourcing by patrimonial institutions. I have already been able to reuse this post as a reading suggestion for a class where I was invited to present eScriptorium.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I had a lot of other activities throughout the year (teaching, presenting at conferences, etc), but, as far as my thesis project is concerned, two of my biggest concerns were 1) reading and 2) refining my research project.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I tried different strategies to read more, but I am a slow reader and my schedule is often fragmented. I have started finding the beginning of a solution in keeping one day of the week totally without meetings, and by always keeping it the same day. I started implementing this during the past semester and it seemed to work: Wednesday was the day I was going to the library or simply dedicating to my homework. On Wednesday, I never scheduled meetings (unless absolutely necessary). Now that I am back in France for 4 months, I need to make sure I am able to keep this routine. On the other hand, I am trying to solve the speed problem by better sorting the references I end up reading in order not to waste time on a text that was actually not a priority.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the things I learned in 2022 and that affects my reading is the usefulness of expanding the types of publications I read. Let me explain. Working at ALMAnaCH, I saw most of my colleagues focus on reading articles and pre-prints. The main objective there is to keep up to date with a state of the art that evolves quickly and for a discipline that is fairly recent. On the other hand, at the Université de Montréal, more emphasis is placed on the conceptual frame of the research. Therefore, many more books and chapters, of disciplines that are not always the same as the envisioned project, make their way into the bibliographies. It might seem obvious to some of you, but it wasn't for me at the start of the year and this is exactly the type of enrichment I was looking for when I went for a &lt;em&gt;cotutelle&lt;/em&gt;.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, as far as refining my research project is concerned, this is something that I didn't start solving before December. At the Université de Montréal, when I apply for a grant, I often have to introduce my research project, including my methodology and the conceptual frame. Writing these texts, it often made me feel like I was not progressing in terms of making my project more precise. I had a general idea of the topic I wanted to work on and which issues I wanted to address in general, but no clear strategy.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I often thought about it during the year, looking for a way to solve this problem. It wasn't a question of narrowing down my topic or use-case, I think mine is/are already well defined. It is only at the occasion of a 20 minutes presentation assigned during the HNU7000 seminar that I sat at a table and put together my thoughts and the results of my discussions with my supervisors. I will soon dedicate a post to the current state of my research project, but what I think I was lacking the most was &lt;strong&gt;an angle&lt;/strong&gt; to efficiently narrow down the scope of my project and justify future choices.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even though I started focusing on how different 2022 looked compared to what I had imagined, I am actually very happy with this year. I met a ton of people who have broadened my horizons on research and academia in general. And I start 2023 full of ideas for my phD and this blog! Keep an eye out for them in future posts!&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>courses</category><guid>https://alix-tz.github.io/phd/posts/009/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 31 Dec 2022 15:14:57 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>