<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="https://alix-tz.github.io/phd/assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>A research (b)log (Posts about cotutelle)</title><link>https://alix-tz.github.io/phd/</link><description></description><atom:link href="https://alix-tz.github.io/phd/categories/cotutelle.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><copyright>Contents © 2023 &lt;a href="https://alix-tz.github.io/phd/"&gt;Alix Chagué&lt;/a&gt; CC-BY</copyright><lastBuildDate>Tue, 14 Nov 2023 09:31:34 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>015 - Block post and comprehensive Exam</title><link>https://alix-tz.github.io/phd/posts/015/</link><dc:creator>Alix Chagué</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;When I created this blog last year, I wanted to post regularly on it. Something like once a month or once every other month. I didn't want to put pressure on myself for writing, but I also wanted to make sure that this blog would be alive. I often have ideas for topics for a post. But then, when comes the time to write, I blank out. It's not exactly that I don't know where to start, it's just that I sometimes can't figure out what is the message I want to convey. Like, if I have to summarize my blog post in 2 lines, what's the take-away? I get stuck when I cannot find an answer,but maybe I shouldn't worry that much about it. It's my blog after all, and maybe the message will come by the time I'm done writing. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, without further ado, let's dive in: I was &lt;em&gt;super&lt;/em&gt; excited this Summer after passing my comprehensive exam. I really wanted to write a post about it. I had a really packed Spring and beginning of Summer between going back to Montreal, teaching a class there, attending a Summer school, going to the DH2023 conference in Austria where I presented a short paper, a long paper and organized a workshop (big up to Thibault who was by my sides through all these Austrian adventures). And all of it culminated with that comprehensive exam in the middle of August. I really wanted to share how that went.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But then, vacations, working on new deadlines, more vacations, more deadlines... And now it's already November and I don't know anymore what it was that I wanted to share about that exam. Aside from the fact that I passed it and that it's a pretty big milestone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The comprehensive examination, which is called "Examen de synthèse" in French, is not something common in France. In France, we now have a sort of yearly evaluation called the "Comité de Suivi Individuel" (or CSI), which is not a scholar evaluation but more of a check-up with your supervisors and a committee&lt;sup id="fnref:CSI"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="https://alix-tz.github.io/phd/posts/015/#fn:CSI"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; in charge of making sure that everything is alright. The reason I bring it alongside the Examen de Synthèse is because I also had my first CSI this Summer (at the very end of June). In France, you have to have a positive evaluation from the CSI in order to enroll in a new year of doctoral studies. Each year. But, actually the CSI and the Examen de Synthèse are not really that comparable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Examen de Synthèse is a "real" examination and it happens only once during your doctoral curriculum. In my program at the University of Montréal, in 2023, it consisted in several phases.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First of all, there is a phase dedicated to the composition of the jury. I had the pleasure to be examined not only by my three supervisors (Laurent Romary, Emmanuel Chateau-Dutier and Michael Sinatra), but also by &lt;a href="https://vitalirosati.com/"&gt;Marcello Vitali Rosati&lt;/a&gt;, from the University of Montréal, who acted as president, and &lt;a href="https://www.uqar.ca/universite/a-propos-de-l-uqar/departements/departement-des-lettres-et-humanites/gohier-maxime"&gt;Maxime Gohier&lt;/a&gt; from the University of Quebec in Rimouski. I must signal that my only regret is not to have been able to have a better gender parity in my jury. This is something I really hope to fix for my defense, but I will probably have other occasions to discuss this topic in the future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, once the jury is composed, and once a calendar has been agreed on (I think &lt;em&gt;that&lt;/em&gt; was actually the most stressful part for me because of all the other things I had this Summer), a count down begins. First, I had to turn in three documents:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a 12-15 page-long essay on my research project;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a 30-reference long bibliography on the field of the Digital Humanities; and&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a short presentation of a proposed "practical" analysis.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then a week later, the jury sent a question&lt;sup id="fnref:question"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="https://alix-tz.github.io/phd/posts/015/#fn:question"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. I was given 1 week (168h exactly) to think about this question and write a response in the form of a 10-15 page-long essay. The jury had between a week and two weeks to read the response before an oral examination took place.&lt;sup id="fnref:remote"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="https://alix-tz.github.io/phd/posts/015/#fn:remote"&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The oral examination has some similarities with a PhD defense. It started with a 20 minute long presentation that I gave where I summarized my research project (10 minutes) and presented a technical analysis (10 minutes). I chose to focus my technical presentation on an experiment I have been conducting and on which I hope to communicate more in the near future. Then, after my presentation, there were two rounds of questions about my research project, my experiment or about the answer I formulated in my essay&lt;sup id="fnref:more"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="https://alix-tz.github.io/phd/posts/015/#fn:more"&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am very happy that such an examination exists in the North American program. It may seem like a lot of stress (and it is), but I found that it is also a very good milestone to progress a lot towards the formalization of a research project. The oral examination is a great opportunity to present a project to people who don't necessarily know what you have been up to before, and it's a really really great occasion to get feedback.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, the question that is sent by the jury, in the case of my program, is thought as a way to get you to think about a topic or a question that is either not tackled enough by your research proposal, or it's an invitation to consider new angles. You're not expected to turn in the perfect answer, of course, with barely a week to write it. But it forces you to form an opinion, explore possible hypotheses and may turn later into a whole chapter for your thesis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The comprehensive exam is a pass/no pass type of examination. There is no grade and if you fail, you can take it a second time. Like I said before at the beginning of this post, I passed. Therefore, starting from Fall 2023, I am now able to enroll as a "en rédaction" student (writing status) which has several consequences. Some seem very symbolic: for example, in English, I can now call myself a PhD candidate instead of a PhD student. But others not so much: tuitions for this new status are &lt;a href="https://registraire.umontreal.ca/droits-de-scolarite/couts-des-etudes/#c14807"&gt;much lower&lt;/a&gt; than when enrolling as a full-time student, dropping from 1,440$CA/trimester to 512$CA/trimester, and I believe this officially gives me the right to teach at graduate level.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The comprehensive exam also marks the end of the phase during which I had to take courses. Now, with this new status, I am invited to focus solely on the redaction of my thesis, which opens up a whole new chapter for my PhD curriculum.&lt;sup id="fnref:pun"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="https://alix-tz.github.io/phd/posts/015/#fn:pun"&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:CSI"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I want to take this occasion to also thank Ariane Pinche and Joana Casenave, who were willing to be the members of my committee for the CSI, for their precious feedback! :) &lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="https://alix-tz.github.io/phd/posts/015/#fnref:CSI" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:question"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The question was the following: "Dans votre projet de recherche apparaît une tension importante: celle entre la spécificité des besoins particuliers de chaque projet et la volonté -- et la nécessité -- de produire des approches généralisables, qui puissent être employées dans le cadre de plusieurs projets. En vous appuyant sur votre bibliographie, et en vous concentrant notamment sur le cas du HTR, pourriez-vous analyser cette tension en soulevant en particulier la question de la littératie demandée (notamment dans la gestion des données) pour pouvoir personnaliser des approches computationnelles aussi complexes que les technologies HTR? &lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="https://alix-tz.github.io/phd/posts/015/#fnref:question" title="Jump back to footnote 2 in the text"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:remote"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Funnily enough, we had to organize this examination remotely by combining 3 timezones: Montréal's, Paris' and Tokyo's. It's not that easy! &lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="https://alix-tz.github.io/phd/posts/015/#fnref:remote" title="Jump back to footnote 3 in the text"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:more"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I want publish on my blog the documents I created for the comprehensive exam, but I need to find the best way to do it. I'll post an announcement when it will be available. &lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="https://alix-tz.github.io/phd/posts/015/#fnref:more" title="Jump back to footnote 4 in the text"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:pun"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thank you Jennifer for this wonderful pun! ;) &lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="https://alix-tz.github.io/phd/posts/015/#fnref:pun" title="Jump back to footnote 5 in the text"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>cotutelle</category><category>courses</category><guid>https://alix-tz.github.io/phd/posts/015/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 07 Nov 2023 13:15:06 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>004 - Cotutelle 101</title><link>https://alix-tz.github.io/phd/posts/004/</link><dc:creator>Alix Chagué</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;By now, you must have understood that I am enrolled in two universities: the &lt;a href="https://www.umontreal.ca/"&gt;Univesité de Montréal&lt;/a&gt; (UdeM), in Montréal, and the &lt;a href="https://www.ephe.psl.eu/"&gt;Ecole Pratique des Hautes Etudes&lt;/a&gt; (EPHE), in Paris. This specific setup, where two universities are involved, is called a "&lt;em&gt;cotutelle&lt;/em&gt;" (or double degree). It does not have to be international, but mine is. It significantly impacts the quantity of paperwork I'm subjected to, and I believe sharing the details of the process can be useful to other people interested in this setup. I'll try to keep it simple, but I also want to cover all the variables that must be taken into account, so buckle up!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'll start with detailing the obligations which come with a &lt;em&gt;cotutelle&lt;/em&gt; (by that I mean what needs to be in place for it to be and remain valid). Then, in the next posts, I'll cover some of the most significant "extra" paperwork I also have to handle, before giving my feedback on the advantages and drawbacks of this setup.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First of all, doing a PhD in &lt;em&gt;cotutelle&lt;/em&gt; means signing up in two institutions. In other words, it means maintaining, at all times, a valid student status in two universities.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the EPHE, enrollment happens once a year, usually in Fall, like in most French universities. Last year, I officially enrolled in November 2021, when my PhD contract started at &lt;a href="https://www.inria.fr/en"&gt;Inria&lt;/a&gt;. It was my understanding that for a PhD, at the EPHE, the deadlines are slightly less stringent than for a Licence or a Master's program. At UdeM, enrollment happens every 4 months, at the beginning of each period (&lt;em&gt;Hiver&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Eté&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Automne&lt;/em&gt;, or Winter, Summer, Fall), as is the case in most North American universities.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A yearly enrollment at EPHE costs about 475€ (380€ for tuition and 95€ for &lt;a href="https://www.etudiant.gouv.fr/fr/cvec-une-demarche-de-rentree-incontournable-955"&gt;CVEC&lt;/a&gt;). At UdeM, it costs a little bit over 6,000 $CA (between 4,650€ and 4,200€, depending on the exchange rate), which corresponds to 3 periods where tuition and other non-waivable fees are added up.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Prior to the very first enrollment, it was necessary to be accepted into each university. For both the EPHE and UdeM, in order to apply for enrollment, I had to fill out forms and send documents like grade transcripts and cover letters. In my excitement to get everything organized, I may have started these processes slightly too early. It forced me to wait a long time before I received an answer. It was particularly the case with the EPHE: I submitted my application via the portal called &lt;a href="https://www.adum.fr/"&gt;ADUM&lt;/a&gt; mid-July, but the EPHE only started processing it at the end of September: I only received the notification of acceptance at the beginning of October. The timeline was similar at UdeM: I submitted my application via their dedicated portal (overall, they have so many interfaces...) at the beginning of June but was only officially admitted in September. The admission at UdeM in September allowed me to start another set of paperwork related to immigration to Canada, but I will cover those in the next post.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once I was successfully admitted and enrolled in both universities, I had 12 months to setup a &lt;em&gt;convention de cotutelle&lt;/em&gt;. It is a contract between UdeM and the EPHE where the details of the &lt;em&gt;cotutelle&lt;/em&gt; are given. For example, it states when I will be in which university and to whom I should pay my tuition. It also specifies who my supervisors are, what the title and scope of my research are, how the jury of my defense will be composed, where the said defense will take place, etc. Each university has its own template, and luckily for me UdeM and EPHE have already had such a partnership in the past, therefore we weren't creating a new process from scratch. The setup of the &lt;em&gt;cotutelle&lt;/em&gt; is mostly handled by the departments of international studies from each university. However, I have been asked to provide information in a more or less formal way from time to time. As of today, the creation of my &lt;em&gt;convention de cotutelle&lt;/em&gt; is still in progress.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Aside from the enrollment and the &lt;em&gt;convention de cotutelle&lt;/em&gt;, the other main obligation is to spend at least 12 months (continuous or not) at each institution. This means I could spend 1 year in Montreal and 2 years in Paris. Or 1.5 years in Montreal and 1.5 in Paris. Otherwise, 2 years in Montreal and 1 year in Paris. The decision is up to me (and also a bit up to my supervisors).  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Besides determining how much I will pay in tuition (you understood earlier that studying in France is much cheaper than in Canada), I had to factor in other obligations in order to determine what my calendar would be for the next three years.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, in order for my UdeM degree to be valid, I have to pass 5 courses at UdeM within the first 2 years of my PhD. All of the available courses are listed in &lt;a href="https://admission.umontreal.ca/programmes/doctorat-en-litterature/structure-du-programme/"&gt;the degree's program&lt;/a&gt; (you should really click on the link and go to segment 78 before you read the next sentences): some of them are required, other are electives. For example, I must take HNU 7000 (and LCO 6000) in order to validate the segment 78A, even if this class is only taught during Fall 2022. But I can choose any course among list given for 78C in order to validate this second segment. Once I have passed the 5 courses, I must then take and pass a &lt;em&gt;comprehensive exam&lt;/em&gt;. Such exam will mark the end of my status as a full-time student and allow me enroll as an official Phd candidate, aka someone who is actually writing their dissertation (in French, simply, "&lt;em&gt;En Rédaction&lt;/em&gt;"). For now, this mostly means that tuition will be much cheaper (each period will cost about 500 $CA against the current ~2,000 $CA/period). Going back to my cotutelle, this obligation meant that I could not wait until the 3d year to go to Montreal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Secondly, I can receive funds from the CRIHN and UdeM (via grants or contracts) only when I am spending the period in Montreal. This means I have to aim for a very balanced ratio between the two universities, because Inria can only fund 1.5 years of my PhD.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These two limitations implied that I had to distribute my time between Montreal and Paris in such a way that I would spend at least 1 year in Montreal during the first 2 years, as well as 6 additional months there, before or after the end of the second year. Because I live with my partner in Paris and did not want to go away for too long, I decided to go for a slightly unusual (and therefore quite complicated) configuration where I spend every other period in Montreal. I will be there for Winter 2022, Fall 2022 and Summer 2023. The rest of the time (Summer 2022, Winter 2023, Fall 2023 and a part of Winter 2024), I will be in Paris. The remaining 6 months to spend in Montreal will probably occur near the end of my third year, in 2024.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This might seem complicated, but if you are interested in going for a &lt;em&gt;cotutelle&lt;/em&gt;, you must understand that my process is more complicated than it has to be. I could have made it simpler by staying 1 year in Paris, then 1 year in Montreal, then splitting the remaining year between Montreal and Paris. Or, had Inria been able to pay me for a longer period of time, I could have simply spent my second year in Montreal and the rest of the time in Paris.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you're still hanging in there, let's talk about immigration, housing and insurance... in the next post!  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;EDIT:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;UdeM offers a very detailed roadmap on how to set up a &lt;/em&gt;cotutelle&lt;em&gt;, it can be reached through &lt;a href="https://esp.umontreal.ca/fileadmin/esp/documents/Cotutelles/TableauRepere_cotutelleDeThese.pdf"&gt;this link&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>cotutelle</category><category>tuition</category><guid>https://alix-tz.github.io/phd/posts/004/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 08 Jun 2022 16:13:01 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>